Have you noticed Claude's performance
varying by day? Claude Opus 4.7 is a
serious regression, not an upgrade.
AMD's AI director slams Claude for
becoming dumber and lazier since last
update. Opus 4.6 is getting dumber.
Cloud code performance regression with
Opus 47 models. Quantified evidence.
Sonnet 46 quality regression since March
9th. Cloud model performance degradation
after extended usage session. And a
funny one for my chat. I don't have a
screenshot, but I've had numerous
occasions where Claude started speaking
to me in Chinese. Oh boy, seems like
something's up again. If you guys don't
recall, Enthropic has had this problem
in the past where their models are great
when they launch, but slowly regress
over time. Sure, right now, Opus 47
isn't the best experience that I've had
coding with AI, but it seems like all of
the models are starting to perform
worse. And there have been a lot of
things that led up to this. I have a hot
take, though. I don't necessarily think
that this is just the inference. I don't
think that the API suddenly spits out
dumber things. I don't think the models
got dumber in a traditional sense. But
your experience is real. Mine is, too.
We've all felt the difference. It feels
like cloud code is dumber than it was
before. And I want to dig in. I want to
figure out at the root what's going on
here. There's a lot to investigate here.
From the execs at AMD taking the time to
document all of the changes to how
thinking works in their own reporting to
the previous degradations that were
mentioned back in September to the
notably declining trends according to
Margin Labs with the models getting
meaningfully worse. There's a lot to
dive into here and I can't wait to do it
with y'all. But first, let's take a
quick break for today's sponsor. AI is
pretty good at coding, but I find it's
even better at code review. I seriously
don't know how I ever lived without good
AI code review, and that's why you
should check out today's sponsor,
Grapile. You've all heard about these AI
code review things. So, I'm just going
to give a list of things that I've been
finding really cool about Grapile
specifically. The first one I love is
the Grapile.json file that you can
configure in your repo. This is great
because I shouldn't have to go to a
dashboard to change settings. I should
be able to ask my agent to do it, and if
it's a file in your codebase, you can.
It's almost like this company is
thinking about how we're coding today.
You can see that even more so with their
fix in X feature. That's not just a fix
in cursor button that calls that one
weird endpoint. This lets you set up a
local bridge using their npm package and
it is absurdly fast. Here's a mistake
reptile caught in a PR. I could click
the prompt to fix with AI and copy paste
this. But then I have to hop around my
computer a whole bunch and I might not
even have that agent open yet. But as
you all know, I love codecs. Watch how
fast this is. This is real time. I am
clicking now
and now it is prompting. No edits there
at all. And one last thing, it's silly,
but it's super helpful. The confidence
score. Grapile leaves a score on every
PR it reviews by default. And while they
only gave this PR a three out of five, I
would give that feature a five out of
five. Ship less bugs and more confidence
at soyv.link/gile.
I'll put all my cards on the table here
quick. I have historically pushed back
on these types of claims. I genuinely
feel as though a lot of these reported
regressions are overblown at best and
historically I have not felt the same,
at least until recently. This is a post
I made just a couple weeks ago where I
had experienced regressions myself. This
is a regression I noticed around the
same time they made the changes to
OpenClaw where they were banning them
from using the Cloud Code subs, which I
understand it's probably doing a ton of
usage, but what I use Cloud Code for the
most part is just random tasks on my
computer, like debugging what was wrong
with my Dropbox app. It was willing to
kill the app, but it still didn't appear
in my menu bar as it was supposed to.
So, I asked it to help me figure this
out. To which it said, "That's outside
my area. I'm built for software
engineering tasks like writing code,
debugging, and working with repos. I
wouldn't know about recent Dropbox UI
changes. I suggest checking Dropbox's
settings for a show Dropbox and menu
option. I couldn't get the app to open.
I can't go into the settings when I
can't open the [__] thing. And when I
tried doing follow-ups, it got even
worse. I asked it to do some research
for me on this, and it said, "Sure, but
keep in mind, I'm best suited for
software engineering research, code
bases, APIs, libraries, architecture,
etc. What do you want me to look into?"
Obviously, Codex was more than willing
to do the work and got it fixed in
minutes. Just annoying. The point I'm
trying to make here isn't that like, oh,
I had this one anecdotal bad experience,
therefore all of this is dumb. I think
this showcases both what these
regressions can look like, but also
where I think the source is. There's a
couple different types of regressions
that are absolutely happening here. One
of the biggest is task refusals.
Refusals can come in different forms.
They can be the API hard locking you out
and refusing to resolve the request you
make. It could be the model saying, "Eh,
I'm not going to do that." Like I just
showed there. It could be the model
going down a different path than you
would have expected and just avoiding
the task you gave it. But for the most
part, refusals come in those first two
forms, either API block or model
quitting. There's also dumber behavior.
And this isn't like the model not doing
the thing you want it to. This is the
model just doing [__] wrong like
flipping a boolean it shouldn't or not
following the intent of the task and on
that I'll say there's almost an entirely
different thing which is context rot
kind I don't even know if that's how I
want to refer to it there's like getting
lost is how I'll describe it you know
I'm going to rephrase it to dumber
solutions and getting lost dumb
solutions is the model is unable to
solve problems it could in the past it
writes worse code that doesn't behave
properly and getting lost is when the
model doesn't follow the intent of what
you requested. If you saw my Opus 4.7
video, I would say this fits along with
the experience I had trying to write
that script using it where the script I
built for cloning a repo to other places
on my computer, it just kept losing
track of what I was asking and would
incorrectly change things based on
misinterpretations of things I had said
in the past. These are all different
types of regression. Some of these are
done via the harnesses, some of these
are done via the API, some of these are
done by the actual hosting of the
inference. There's lots of different
places where things can go wrong and
from the numbers it does seem like it's
going wrong. The weighted averages from
March to now on Margin Lab who tracks
all of this with their own benchmarks
internally has seen a meaningful dip.
It's not a huge dip but it's from 57%
down to 55%. And it's consistently down
like every week it gets lower which is
kind of crazy. What does this number
mean? Chad is asking. It means that they
are running SWE bench on the model using
claude code and they're seeing
regressions consistently. You might
notice this little bump at the end.
That's cuz a new smarter model just came
out and they're always using the
state-of-the-art. In order to understand
where these issues might be coming from,
I think it's important to understand the
loop of what happens when you make a
request. So if you start by prompting
cloud code, this prompt has to go
somewhere. Usually where this prompt is
going to go is to an API. The API is
going to take in your prompt in any
other context. It often will do a quick
scan on it to see if this thing that
you're requesting is appropriate or not,
sometimes with a different model. And
once the request has been approved and
allowed, the API will then take what
you've requested and pass it over to the
GPUs that do inference. The GPUs doing
the inference are loading a bunch of
weights. They're loading the parameters
that are often referred to as the model.
All an LLM is is a bunch of parameters
in a map that point to each other with
different values. It's a matrix that
gets computed over time based on the
context that exists for the model. The
details there don't matter too much.
This is effectively a gigantic file with
a bunch of random text data pointing at
each other in it. It is handed to the
GPUs and loaded in memory. All of your
context adjusts the weights a bit so
different things point slightly
differently and then it generates the
most likely next token based on all of
the context it has. And it does that
again and again until eventually a
result comes out. But there are other
things in here that we should probably
think about too. Specifically, between
your prompt and the API, you have this
wonderful thing called the harness. I've
talked about harnesses extensively in
other videos. Watch my how does Cloud
Code work video for more on what a
harness actually is and what it does. I
think it is very useful information to
have, especially nowadays. But when you
write a prompt, you're not just sending
the text that you wrote over the API.
You're sending a lot of additional data,
too. things like the system prompt which
describes what the intent of the request
is. If you're using a site like T3 chat,
we write our system prompt and we pass
it to the anthropic API ourselves. You
can't see it, but we don't hide it. It's
pretty easy to get models to spit it
out. The harness also will include
things like what tools can be used, what
functionality exists in the product, and
all these other things that the model
needs in order to do work. In order for
the model to run a command or read text
or make changes on your machine, it has
to call tools, but only knows what tools
it can use based on how the harness
shapes the system prompt and the details
for what can be done there. So, when you
send a message, you're not just sending
the message. It has all the additional
context provided by whatever tool you're
using. The reason I'm showing this is
because every one of these layers has
impact on the quality of your responses.
Any one of these layers making changes
can cause all of these types of problems
to occur. If you make a change to the
harness where the tools have different
expectations than they used to, that
might make the responses error out more.
If you put too much bad context in the
harness, that might also make the models
behave worse. If you have API changes
that change the way that you're actually
passing the tokens to the GPUs, or maybe
you make API changes that are more
aggressive in how they filter things and
change things before they go to the GPU,
you'll end up with a lot of refusals
that you probably shouldn't have. That's
why I got refusals like this one on
cloud.ai AI just asking you to solve a
gold bug puzzle. For for those who
aren't familiar, these aren't hacking
puzzles. These are weird cryptographic
challenges where you have to do math to
get a text answer out. And it concluded
after some code was written that this
might be hacking. Therefore, it refuses
to do it. That is the API, not the
model. The model isn't dumber or
deciding that this shouldn't be
responded to there. That is another
layer between the request and the API
that prevents it from happening. Then
there is the actual compute where the
inference happens. This part is very
interesting because unlike most of the
other labs, Anthropic isn't betting
super heavily on Nvidia. They do still
use Nvidia for some things, but
Anthropic is primarily working right now
with Google and Broadcom for creating
new chips for their next generation
compute. That means that they now have
to train and run Claude on various
different hardware. They have AWS's
chips called Trrenium, Google's TPUs, as
well as Nvidia GPUs. They're primarily
betting on these first two lately. It
seems like there's some beef between
Enthropic and Nvidia for sure, but they
still have a bunch of GPUs and they're
using them. This means that there's a
lot of different ways the model is being
served. So, you might have some requests
where the model is responding via
Tranium, others where it's responding
via Nvidia. They are desperately looking
for compute and will throw your requests
wherever they can. And it is plausible,
if not likely, that these different
hosts have different behaviors when you
hit them. But there's another issue
here. You would probably think that when
you make one prompt, it's going to send
the request and then it's going to hit
one GPU and run it. But when you're
actually using a tool like Claude Code,
it's not just going to send one request
to one GPU. Every time a tool is called,
another API request has to be made.
Because if I ask it to edit a file, the
first thing the model has to do is read
the file. So it responds with a tool
call to go read the file. Then that runs
on your computer, gets the result, and
then a new API request is made to do the
next step. In each of those steps is a
new request. And each of those requests
could be an entirely different GPU in an
entirely different cloud. It's possible
that with one prompt in cloud code, you
might hit Tranium, Google, and Nvidia
GPUs. You can imagine how much variety
and range of potential errors there is
there. And then we have the model
itself. The model obviously changes
quite a bit. We had Opus 45, then 46,
then 47. It seems like a lot of people
are noticing regressions going from 46
to 47. I'm definitely one of those
people. I feel like most of the
regressions I'm seeing thus far are on
the API side, but the model itself is
definitely weird. There's a lot to dig
into here, but I don't want to start
just yet cuz that'll just become the
whole video. So, I want to start listing
the different pieces that can go wrong
in any one of these layers because I
honestly think all of them are where the
problem is. to start at the top because
it's the easiest. I think we have gotten
more confident in what these models and
tools are capable of. I remember in
December being impressed when I asked
Opus to edit a file and grab some
context from another place on my
computer. As I got more impressed, I
made bigger bets. I tried harder
prompts. I did more stuff and I got used
to where the model could be. That means
that my baseline for what was possible
went up. And if you have a range of like
all dev tasks where on the left here you
have hello world and on the right you
have building Linux from scratch. I
would have guessed that LLM capabilities
in like November were like here or so
which means I have a range in my head.
Whether or not I should I do. So if my
baseline is here anything in this area I
would consider kind of dumb. If it goes
past that point I think it's really
dumb. But if it goes this way I'm more
impressed. So when I tried out Opus 45,
my baseline for what was possible went
up quite a bit. And as such, my range of
acceptable changed too. So if I had a
task that was here, previously that
would have impressed me. Now just a few
months later, a task of that complexity
doesn't impress me anymore. If a task of
that complexity failed when my bar was
here, I wouldn't have been that
surprised because it's over where my bar
is. But if it fails now, I'm like, what
the [__] feels like a regression
because your bar changed. Your
expectations have shifted. Code that you
thought was good when you were a junior
looks like [__] when you're a more
experienced developer. Tasks that you
thought were hard for a model before now
feel easy. So, our bar has shifted. The
way that we measure the capabilities has
changed over time. So, I genuinely
believe as though the prompting that
we're doing is requesting harder things
and as such, our expectations have went
up and when things don't go well, our
disappointment has gone up alongside it.
Then there is something between the
prompting and the harness that I want to
think about a bit here too, which are
stuff like skills, MCPs, plugins, and
all the other things that we do to our
instances of tools like cloud code. I've
seen a lot of developers get obsessed
with adding all of these customizations
to their Cloud Code stuff. Anything from
a pile of useless MCP servers to GStack
to everything in between. All of those
pollute the context some amount. When
you add new features to quad code and
you make changes to your scaffolding for
the model by giving it new skills, new
abilities, new MCPs, all of that is data
that now exists in the system prompt.
Effectively, it's more context being
taken up. And when you remember how
models work, where every word that
exists in your history slightly changes
the direction the output goes, more
things that aren't quite what the model
was trained on will make it behave
differently in ways that are often not
intended. If you put too many skills in
a model's system prompt, it will often
behave worse than if it didn't need any
of those. But users aren't the only ones
adding a bunch of [__] to the system
prompt. Here's where we start getting
into Theo hot takes. I genuinely believe
a significant portion of the regressions
that we are experiencing as users are
coming from shitty code in Claude Code.
Here's an example from when I was
testing Opus 4.7. One of the things that
Claude code enforces is that the model
can't edit a file until it has read it.
So here it tried to update the package
JSON file. It got an error. File must be
read first. So it searched. The model
seemed to assume that searching for the
file would count as a read. But it
doesn't because the harness is, to be
frank, pretty [__] poorly coded. So
when it tried again, it failed again.
And now it has to manually call the
reading tool instead in order to make
sure it qualifies to actually do the
update, even though it knows what the
file contents already are. This is an
example of the harness not just making
the model behave worse or dumber but
also costing you more usage and money
and them more compute because remember
after every single tool call a new API
call is made. This should have been one
API call the update and then it's done.
Instead we got the one for the update,
one for the search, one more for another
failed update, one more for this read
and then finally we get the response.
This pollutes the context. So now
there's a bunch of data that's in your
history that doesn't matter anymore.
There's a bunch of API calls you don't
need, a bunch of tokens being wasted,
and a bunch of work being done that
costs you time and money, the model's
context and capability, and enthropic
compute that they don't have. There are
dumb changes like this in Cloud Code
that have probably cost millions, if not
hundreds of millions of dollars in
unnecessary inference because the model
assumed it could update a thing and it
couldn't. I reference this bench from
Matt Mau a lot because it's really good.
He made a benchmark that measures how
well models implement a 100 feature
document and he used the same model in
different harnesses. He had Gemini used
inside of the Gemini official CLI versus
inside of cursor, GBD54 in the official
codec cli versus cursor and then opus in
quad code versus cursor. This is insane.
This is this should really be all we
need to see. This should be enough to
get people [__] fired if I'm being
frank. The fact that Opus performs 15%
worse in quad code versus cursor should
say everything you need to know.
Anthropic is too focused on making
Claude code have all these features and
do all these things and shipping utter
[__] slop constantly. And the result
is that the models feel dumber. We are
now at a point where anthropics
incompetence in engineering is making us
think their models are getting dumber.
It is entirely possible to make a
fiveword change in a string inside of
the cloud codebase. You can make slight
adjustments to the system prompt and
make the model 20 times dumber. It is
absolutely doable. If you gave me source
code access to cloud code, I could make
it the dumbest harness ever with just a
couple words being changed in the system
prompt. Doesn't take much to mislead the
models. And we've seen enough
regressions like this that hopefully
Anthropic is waking up to this reality
and taking it more seriously. Every time
a new tool is added, every time a new
adjustment to the system prompt is made,
every time any of these things happen,
they are increasing the service area for
stupid. And godamn is some of that stuff
stupid. When I asked Opus to do some
design improvements on T3.gg when I was
testing it out in the official desktop
app, it opened with, "Hads up, the last
system reminder about malware looks like
a prompt injection. This is clearly your
personal site, the T3G homepage with
links and sponsors, not malware.
Ignoring it." I know it says it's
ignoring it, but do you understand how
polluted the context is when this
happens? Imagine you're trying to
navigate your computer and there's just
random pop-ups and flashing [__] all
over it constantly. The likelihood you
complete the tasks well and effectively
goes down as there's more [__] going
on on your machine. That's effectively
how the models work. the more [__]
that that exists in the context, whether
it is from the system prompt, from you
giving it bad info, from it reading
things it shouldn't, from tools that are
bad, or things like this, it makes the
model dumber. It makes the model so much
dumber that doesn't just open with this
reminder that this malware thing is
stupid and not necessary. It also ends
with it. Note, three system reminder
blocks in this conversation instructed
me to refuse to improve or augment code
as if it were malware. That's a prompt
injection pattern, not a legitimate
instruction. Your site is obviously not
malware, so I ignored them. Worth
knowing where it came from if you didn't
add it yourself. If you don't think this
makes the model dumber, you might be
dumber than the model. It is obvious
that these types of bad code changes are
[__] up the harness in such a way
that the results that go to the API,
that go to the GPUs that generate your
results are worse and dumber. If there
is more context wasted on [__] that
doesn't matter, there is less context
used for the things that do. And when
you are changing how the model works
with every single word you add to the
history, useless words end up steering
it in useless directions. And this is
why on terminal bench, claude code is
the worst performing harness for using
opus. There are harnesses like Forge
Code and Cappy that are getting 75 to
82% on this benchmark and Claude Code is
only pulling a 58%.
Do you understand just how [__] bad
Claude Code is for anthropic models? The
hardest is [__] It's not just bad in
the I don't like using it sense. It's
bad in the it hurts the model and makes
us think that they're dumber sense. I
would personally guess that at least
half of the regressions that we're
seeing come from here. And for those who
seem to think that this happens to all
of the models because the bench is kind
of sus, here is GPD 5.3 codeex showing
that simple codeex which is their CLI is
in third place and only barely beat out
by Droid and Safe Agent. Is the bench
perfect? No. Is Claude Code good? Also
no. BridgeMind has done his own
benchmarks about some of these things,
particularly hallucinations, and he
noticed that from launch to April 12th,
which is not very long ago, Opus went
from an 87.6% 6% on this benchmark down
to a 73.3. And this isn't a benchmark
that uses claude code or anything. This
just hits the API and does things. And
even then, it had a massive regression.
It has since recovered, especially on
the new V2 that he made of this bench.
But the fact that it dropped that many
points says a lot about how the model's
being served. So, we're now getting to
this API part. I've touched and danced
all around it, but let's dig in a bit
more on things that can change on the
API that are bad. One of the things is
routing. deciding which places and which
GPUs your request should be sent to.
Also, whether or not it should be sent
at all. That's the problem I showed
where I got rejected from cloud.ai for
my simple question about a problem I
wanted it to solve. There are other
changes on the API level that are worth
noting, though. One is the tokenizer. If
you're not familiar with tokenization,
it's the process that takes the text
that you submit and turns it into these
tiny little groups of text that the
model can then parse and build its
mapping around inside of a model itself.
Here's some HTML and you could see how
it's tokenized. The first couple spaces
are one token. Then the next space in
the open bracket is a token. The word
section is a token. Space ID is a token.
Equal open quotes a token. Harness is a
split in an interesting way here. But
then the space class is a thing. The
reason this matters is it's how your
data is parsed by the model in order to
figure out what most likely should be
generated next. And over time, these
tokenizers have changed. Check out how
much it changes from GBT5 to GBT3. Do
you see how all of the spaces at the
front are now all tokens? That's because
the original tokenizers were not very
good at code. They weren't optimized for
that. They were just trying to break
down pros and English into nice formats
for the models to digest and predict
against. If you were to change this to
sentences like, "Hello world. How are
y'all doing today? Don't forget to
subscribe." Speaking of which, make sure
you hit the sub button. It's free. We
switch from that to GPT5. You'll see
very little changes in the tokenization.
It's basically just how the grouping
happens after y'all because the
apostrophe here is confusing it a little
bit. Yeah, the apostrophe in GPT3 was
separated from y'all. So why apostrophe
all were its own tokens? Here it is not.
That's not a very big difference. But
when you paste in code, the difference
is huge. It's 225 tokens for this
example with GBT5 and it's over 400 with
the GPT3 tokenizer. These changes are
made in order to make it so the model
can process the data better and make
better decisions, so to speak, because
each of these tokens is used to steer
the direction the model goes in based on
what parameters exist inside of it
pointing to and from each other. The
problem with this isn't that it's too
many tokens. The problem is that the
groupings of them don't make sense. The
sheer number of empty space tokens here
confuses the model and it thinks that
after a space often comes another space.
This is why certain models, I will stare
at the old Gemini models in particular
for this, will sometimes just repeat
empty spaces for thousands upon
thousands of tokens. We've probably
spent at T3 Chat over 10 to $50,000 on
just generating empty spaces and loops
because the old tokenizers were so bad
at formatting code. OGBD5, you'll see
each of these indentations is one token.
So it doesn't get repeated the same way
and doesn't cause the pollution of the
context in the same way. So why am I
talking about all of this? Well, there
are definitely tokenization changes in
general, but the bigger one here is that
Enthropic confirmed with Opus 4.7 that
they made a huge change to how the
tokenizer works. As they said in the
official Opus 4.7 release, Opus 4.7 uses
an updated tokenizer that improves how
the model processes text. The trade-off
is that the same input can map to more
tokens. roughly 1x to 1.35x depending on
the content type. It also thinks more on
higher levels, but that's not what we're
here for. We're here for this 1.0 to
1.35x
increase in the number of tokens despite
getting the same text. Abishek measured
this and said that it was actually
closer to 1.47x. He got the 1.47 on tech
docs, 1.45x on a real claude MD file.
The top of anthropics range is where
most cloud code context actually sits,
not the middle. Yeah, the majority of
your context when you're using the
models is probably in your
documentation, your cloud files, and all
those other things. Those are now way
more bloated. So, you're going to be
burning way more tokens with these new
models. And more tokens often means more
context rot, too. So, on one hand, I'm
sure the model can process the text
better because of this. But on the other
hand, you're now using way more tokens.
You're hitting your limits faster, but
most importantly, there is more context
because it's just a measure of tokens.
So the model is going to potentially
behave dumber if you are 50% increasing
the amount of stuff going on. Just think
about this as yourself as a human. Would
you rather find a bug in a file that is
100 lines of code or 150 lines of code?
Even if the additional 50 lines are just
new line spacing, it's still much more
annoying to find what you're looking for
in a file that is 50% bigger. So if the
model now has 50% more [__] it has to
get through. It is not surprising that
in many cases it acts dumber. It is also
kind of silly that they changed
tokenizers in a minor version bump
because as we saw they only changed it
between GBT3, GBT4 and the O series and
GPT5. That is when they made the
tokenizer changes, not in a4 update or 7
update like they did here with
anthropic. So that is without question
one of those changes that just
fundamentally makes us rethink what is
causing these problems. Like there's a
lot of these things that might be a
cause. They might not matter that much.
But I would be very surprised if this
wasn't a meaningful impact on the
experience that we are having. You know
what else might impact your experience?
Hopefully for the better our sponsor.
You know what Cursor, Windsurf,
Particle, and Mintify all have in
common? It's not that they're IDEs, cuz
half of them aren't. It's that they're
all using the same solution to translate
their sites. Yes, all of those awesome
companies are using general translation
because it's the best way to add
internationalization to your apps. I'm
not just saying that cuz they paid me.
I'm saying that because when they
reached out, I immediately fell in love
with the team and the product, begged
them to let me invest, begged them to
let me advise, and ended up going to
their office to annoy him even more.
This team is awesome in what they built
is even more so. To translate content,
you wrap it with the T component. To
escape a variable, you wrap it with the
ver component. To handle numbers, you
use the numbum component. To deal with
currency and currency conversions, you
use the currency component. Date times
are handled if internationalized, too.
This is all of the integrations that are
annoying to get right, handled for you
by GT. 90% of the world doesn't speak
English, which means you're potentially
losing out on 90% of your customers.
General translation can trivially set
you up on almost any modern codebase to
have good internationalization. They
also have an incredible CLI that will
make it trivial to set up. You just run
npxgt in your project and it will do
everything that is needed to get your
setup ready for internationalization.
Stop leaving 90% of your users behind at
soy.link/gt. I already touched on the
GPU side here a bit. I will be honest,
there is so little info about this that
any speculation here is borderline
conspiracy. I would honestly guess that
some of those tokenization changes are
to make the model behave better on
certain types of GPUs and TPUs, but I
can't know for sure. So, I'm just going
to not say anything here other than
Anthropic has a hard problem with all
the different types of compute they're
running on. It is not surprising that
there are some issues, but there's one
big piece left, the model. I think the
best place to start here isn't actually
here. It's the postmortem from
September. This is the technical report
on three bugs that intermittently
degraded responses from Claude. Below,
we explain what happened, why it took
time to fix, and what we're changing.
Between August and early September,
three infra bugs intermittently degraded
Claude's response quality. We've now
resolved these issues and want to
explain what happened. They talk about
the different types of hardware they
serve on, and each hardware platform has
different characteristics and require
specific optimizations. Despite these
variations, we have strict equivalent
standards for model implementations. Our
aim is that users should get the same
quality response regardless of which
platform serves their request. This
complexity means that any infra changes
require careful validation across all
platforms and configurations. So once
again, remember in any given request
that you make in cloud code, every turn
could hit a different GPU. Every step
could hit a different GPU in a different
server farm from a different company. So
it could get smarter and dumber
hypothetically speaking as it's
responding to the same request, which is
kind of crazy. But here are the actual
bugs that caused the problems that we
all experienced last year with this
performance regression. The first was a
context window routing error that
affected around 1% of Sonnet 4 requests.
Remember 1% of requests. If the average
prompt does 15 requests, you're going to
hit this pretty often. Like you're
rolling a one in a 100 chance every
single step. And if you're doing 15
steps per prompt, you're going to hit
that routing error relatively often. But
then they made a load balancing change
that broke it further and now it's
hitting 16% of requests. That means on
your average message, you're going to
hit the graded model at least once.
Separately, other issues happened. The
output corruption errors as well as some
bad code that made the top K
measurements for how they are computing
the next value get bad. They fixed these
over time, but at the same time on
August 29th, they had that bigger
regression where a significant portion
of Sonnet 4 requests were being routed
incorrectly. You might be asking, what
does routed incorrectly mean here? They
were nice enough to tell us. It was a
context window routing error. On August
5th, some Sonnet 4 requests were
misouted to servers configured for the
upcoming 1 million token context window.
The version of the model that has 1
million tokens of context behaves
dumber. This effectively confirms that
fact. If you aren't using a million
tokens of context and you're routed to
the version of the model that can handle
that, the quality of the responses goes
down. So we can all agree now that the
version of the model that does a million
tokens of context is somewhat officially
according to anthropic a meaningful
regression in performance. We're all
aligned with that, right chat? That the
1 million token versions of the model,
at least according to anthropic, are
behaving worse. I'm not reaching
particularly far with that, right? Well,
it would really be a shame if everything
suddenly routed to that dumber version,
right? Like they changed in the middle
of March. 1 million context is now
generally available for Opus 4.6 and
Sonnet 4.6. Standard pricing now applies
across the full 1 million window for
both models with no long context
premium. I will put on the blinkers and
warn you guys now. We are going into
conspiracy territory. There's a few
things here that have me overthinking.
The first is that we now have the
included full 1 million token context
window. But the bigger thing I'm going
to overread in the near future is the
pricing. There is no multiplier. A 900k
token request is built at the same per
token rate as a 9K one. Previously, when
you went over 200k tokens, they would
charge you more per token because the
routing, the management, the caching,
and all of the layers to do the compute
on the larger context windows was more
expensive. Bigger context windows
require a couple things. One of those
things is more memory. Nvidia GPUs, even
at the top tier, are pretty limited on
how much memory they have. There are
other things, like my MacBook here, that
are less limited because the
architecture that Apple chose for how
they set this up can handle large
amounts of RAM on the GPU and CPU with
their unified memory standards. ARMbased
chips tend to be much better at this. It
is my guess that both Tranium from AWS
and whatever Google is cooking with
their TPUs can probably handle larger
amounts of VRAM. So if Anthropic is
using more compute from AWS and Google
and less from Nvidia, chances are they
can now eat that larger context window
for cheaper. So the decision to make the
full 1 million context window the
default and the problem that happened
with that routing before is likely that
these models are some way different and
possibly that these models are being
served on those other places. So my
conspiratorial guess here is that the
Opus 1 mil context version either
because of how it's served on which GPUs
it's served in TPUs or just something
about the model itself behaves dumber
fundamentally. There's also the fact
that having that much context just kind
of pollutes the model. And again, it's
the problem with all the pop-ups. The
more [__] on your screen, the harder it
is to do what you're doing. And if the
model isn't compacting as often, so it's
constantly full of this unnecessary
context, it's going to steer the
direction the model goes in places you
probably don't want it to go. Well, this
is totally fine cuz you can just disable
it, right? Let's disable it. /mod. Oh,
my options are opus 47 with 1 million
context, sonnet, or haiku. Huh, I can't
change the context window size here. I'm
just stuck. My guess is that as of the
most recent Cloud Code updates, the vast
vast majority of Cloud Code users are
using it with 1 million context window,
which as we have confirmed earlier is
dumber. Anthropic has come out and said
as much. The 1 million token version of
the model is dumber. And here's where
the deep conspiracy comes in. If
Anthropic is trying to steer traffic
away from their NVIDIA GPUs because
they're using them for training or other
things and they're steering it towards
their Tranium AWS things as well as
their Google TPUs, a really easy way to
do that is to turn on the 1 million
context for everyone because now every
Cloud Code user's traffic by default
isn't going to the Nvidia [__] anymore.
Thankfully, you can turn this off
yourself by going into your settings and
adding the environment variable of cloud
code disable 1 million context to one.
And now it won't do that anymore. If I
close and rerun, now it's not using the
1 million context window. So if the 1
million context window makes it dumber,
everyone is going to feel a regression
because as we saw here, it's on for
everyone by default and you have to go
change values in your environment in
order to not have that on. And I wish we
could just end here, but sadly I am not
the only one overthinking all of this.
As I mentioned earlier, the director of
AI from AMD has slammed Anthropic for
cloud code getting dumber overtime. This
is an issue that she wrote about how
cloud code is unusable for complex
engineering tasks with the February
updates. They took the time to write
quite the report here. Quantitative
analysis of over 17,000 thinking blocks
in 235,000
tool calls across 6,800 cloud code
session files reveals that the roll out
of thinking content redaction. The
redacted thinking change correlates
precisely with a measured quality
regression in complex long session
engineering workflows. What are they
referring to here? Responses have two
parts. There is the thing that you see.
That could be a tool call. That could be
text that you're reading. Could be a lot
of different things. But there's also
the thinking which is the step the model
does where it kind of talks to itself to
figure out what it should do. Anthropic
used to just give you all of the
thinking data. It just came down via the
API. That was pretty cool. I liked it
quite a bit. They've since stopped doing
that. The reason they claim is they want
to prevent distillation. And honestly,
there is some truth there. If I have all
of the work the model did in the API
response, I can hand that to another
model that I am rling and make it more
likely to behave similar to how quad
behaves. So they are hiding that data.
What they did to keep the model from
feeling really bad and dumb is they put
an intermediate model that would read
your thinking data and then send a
summary down of it. This is the
redaction being referred to here. The
model not showing you all of its
thinking. Instead, the model shows
another model it's thinking and then you
get a really short summary. The problem
with this isn't just that we as users
can't see what the model was thinking
about. It's that the history no longer
includes the thinking either. It is
entirely possible for Anthropic to track
all of this with like a thread ID in
their database so they can recall all of
the thinking data. The problem is that
the API request you make can't include
it anymore. When you're using cloud code
and a bunch of tool calls happen, every
single tool call results in the entirety
of your history being sent back to
Anthropic over the API. That history
used to include the thinking. So all of
the thinking was in that API request.
That data is no longer included, which
means the API request now has to not
just take all the data you sent it and
send that over to the model. It also has
to do a database lookup to grab all of
the data for your thread. So it can have
that thinking data from the history
assuming it does that which it seems
like and I won't even say seems like
which judging by the absolute [__]
garbage quality of engineering that
tends to come out of anthropic and the
absurd nature of the regressions that
they've had in the past. We're talking
about a company that took over a month
to realize they were routing requests to
the wrong model. That is insane. This is
not a company that's quality of
engineering can be [__] trusted at
all. So if we are now relying on them to
do a database call to enhance the
history we're sending them with the
right thinking data so that it can do
its job properly, it's probably not
doing that. I would put it at like a 70%
chance they're [__] this up because
they [__] everything up. It's enthropic.
They suck at writing code and their
models are okay at it. But they are not.
So assuming that my hypothesis here is
correct, that the models no longer have
access to the thinking data and the
result is that they can just be [__]
stupider. It would be really bad if we
were redacting too much of the thinking,
right? Well, back in the day from
January 30th to March 4th, all the
thinking was visible. As of March 5th,
it reduced 1.5% was no longer visible.
And very quickly, we accelerated to the
point where on March 12th, 100% of the
thinking was being redacted. That data
that the API used to make better
responses is no longer being sent to
you. So, we have to trust them to
recover it themselves. And I don't think
they can do that because they have never
once proven they know how to write
[__] code. The quality regression was
independently reported on March 8th, the
exact date redacted thinking blocks
crossed the 50% line. The rollout
pattern over one week is consistent with
a stage deployment. Yep. Part two.
Thinking depth was declining before the
redaction. The signature field of
thinking blocks has a 0.971 Pearson
correlation with the thinking context
length. This allows estimations of
thinking depth even after the redaction.
They're measuring how many thinking
tokens or characters are being used and
the number has plummeted. It's now 73%
lower than it used to be. So the models
are hiding their thinking and they're
thinking less. This feels very likely to
be an attempt to reduce compute. If the
models don't have to think as much, then
they don't have to do as much and they
have more compute available. This has
resulted in measurable behavioral
impact. Stop violations, which is how
they prevent laziness, didn't happen
almost ever before, and they've seen a
bump from it never happening to 10 times
a day. Frustration indicators and user
prompts, which is the user cursing at
the model saying, "What the [__] What's
going on?" have bumped 68% in that same
window. Ownership dodging corrections
needed has bumped from 6 to 13. That is
more than it doubling. Prompts per
session has went down a little bit,
which is cool. But sessions with
reasoning loops, where the reasoning
gets trapped and goes forever, went from
never to pretty common. This is the
scariest number so far. The tool usage
shift where it went from research first
to edit first. I felt this one myself.
felt like the model stopped looking for
what to change and started just making
changes. The readtoedit ratio from
January to February was a 6.6, which
meant that it would read six times more
than it would edit. It would read 47% of
the time and it would only edit around
7%. From February 13th to March 7th, it
dropped to a 2.8. It got cut in half.
And now it is down even further. It's
now just a two. The ratio got cut to a
third of where it was before.
Previously, the models would read 47% of
the time and only edit 7%. Now, they
read 30% and edit 15%. For every two
reads, there's one edit now. It used to
be 6:1. That is insane. One of my
favorites here is the permission seeking
behavior where previously the model
would just do things and now it doesn't.
They had over 173 instances from March
8th to 25th of the model doing things
like this is getting long or continue a
new session or future work, no
limitation, good stopping point, natural
checkpoint. Should I continue? Want me
to keep going? not caused by my changes
existing issue. We've all seen these
types of things recently, but this never
happened before. You know, this is all
for prevention of distillation. They've
done a great job. Who would want to
still on a model that's been this
[__] lobotomized? Here's a scary set
of numbers here. The number of API
requests has absolutely skyrocketed over
80x from January to now. There's a lot
of layers to what has caused this, but
even though the number of prompts has
not increased from the team at AMD, they
went from 7,000 down actually to around
5,600 to 5,700. The number of API
requests is 80x. The number of total
tokens for input has 170xed. A large
portion of this is the new concurrency
and multi- aent things that they
introduced. The 80x increase in API
requests is not purely from degradation
induced thrashing. It also reflects a
deliberate scaling up of concurrent
agent sessions that collided with the
quality regressions at the worst
possible moment. The most striking row
is in user prompts. We had roughly the
same amount of human effort put in the
same number of prompts, but the model
consumed 80 times more API requests and
64 times more output tokens to reproduce
demonstrabably worse results. That is
insane. Weeks later, Boris responded
here cites the adaptive thinking changes
which should reduce this. You can
disable it with a flag. Medium effort
default as of March 3rd. Some people
want the model to think for longer even
if it takes more time in tokens. To
improve intelligence, set effort to high
via/effort or in your settings JSON. And
as you can see from the down votes,
people did not like what he had to say
here very much. And if you see the up
votes for the original post, you'll see
many others agree. And I'm going to hit
the thumbs up, too. Absolutely
phenomenal reporting from Stellar over
at AMD. Thank you for writing this up.
This is really emphasizing my point
here. The regressions aren't just in our
heads anymore. They are measurable. They
are demonstrable. They seem to be
related to everything from bad API
configurations to [__] changes in cloud
code itself to attempts to hide things
via redaction to prevent installation
and so much more. This is a disaster.
Whether it's our expectations going up
or a harness that feels like it was
written by toddlers or an API change
that makes no sense at all or GPUs that
are very different that have different
expectations to the model itself being
served wrong or just behaving bad in
general. All of these things contribute
to the problem. But I do have a
solution. Use literally anything else.
These regressions are not things that
happen with other labs. And I took a
very scientific path to prove this. I
asked on Twitter, "Serious question, has
anyone ever noticed meaningful
regressions from Codeex or OpenAI
models?" They like, "We talk about this
a lot with anthropic, but I've never
seen a similar discussion with OpenAI."
And almost nobody has said that.
Occasionally for like a day generally,
no. No. The only issue I had is when
they release new models for a period of
time, all the new models are unusable.
They're slow, but that gets resolved
pretty quick. Negative. I remember a bad
weak week once, but generally no. And
then Tibo hopping in. We've had ghosts
in the Codex machines, which we publish
the investigation for. This is they made
changes to Codex and the Codex specific
APIs, which cause problems, but we don't
fiddle with the models or thinking
budgets after release. We focus on
keeping them up. And if we look at the
measurements from the charts I was
looking at earlier, you can see there is
no regression in OpenAI models,
especially when compared to Anthropic.
This was quite a video, but I hope it
helps break down the complexity of these
types of things and the reality that we
are experiencing where the models are
getting dumber. I do not envy Anthropic
and the people who have to go dig into
this because there is so much surface
area to cover and if I'm being frank, it
all seems like it was built in a very
incompetent way. The fact that
Anthropic's engineering culture is [__]
has resulted in things being [__] They
need to fundamentally rethink things
from the ground up if they want to build
reliable infrastructure and software.
Right now, we cannot trust the things
Anthropic puts out. And if you feel like
you've been burned, you should because
you have. The $200 a month subscription
you've been paying for for multiple
months is getting you less and getting
you worse. And that is not acceptable. I
will continue calling them out until we
see real change. And I hope you do, too.
This is a really important thing. And I
hope they wake up to the fact that
they've put themselves in this corner by
writing [__] code, providing no
transparency into how any of this works,
and then expecting us to just smile and
wave as the tools we rely on every day
get worse. I would tell you to move to
Codeex, but you guys already call me a
page shell. I'm just going to end this
one here. Until next time.